YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program: Series IV. Constituent Groups
Sophia Smith Collection
YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 06. Program: Series IV. Constituent Groups
1870-2002
Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.
324_rg6_s4
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
This series includes records of the constituent groups of the YWCA and is arranged in five subseries: Employed Women; Immigration and Foreign Communities; Interracial/Racial Justice; Teenage and Younger Girls; and Young Adults. This series forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 6. Program.
Forms part of the YWCA of the U.S.A. Records--Record Group 6. Program.
NOTE: For the most part, the Microfilmed Records and the Original Format Records do not duplicate each other and both should be consulted. This description covers materials in both formats. See the Contents List for a folder-level inventory of the Original Format Records. See the Microfilmed Records Reel Lists for a detailed inventory of the microfilm.
This Series is divided into five Subseries:
A. EMPLOYED WOMEN
B. IMMIGRATION AND FOREIGN COMMUNITIES
C. INTERRACIAL/RACIAL JUSTICE
D. TEENAGE AND YOUNGER GIRLS
E. YOUNG ADULTS
SUBSERIES A. EMPLOYED WOMEN Historical Note
The Young Women's Christian Association movement was founded to address concerns about the welfare of young, single working women who had moved to urban areas for jobs. Individual Associations in Cities and Towns offered them a range of services (such as housing, job placement, and cafeterias); vocational, recreational, and enrichment opportunities (such as classes, concerts, libraries, and gymnasium facilities); and prayer groups and other religious activities to serve their mental, moral, physical, and spiritual welfare. The idea was to introduce working women to a life beyond drudgery and to offer the potential for self-expression and job training. [See RECORD GROUP 2. PREDECESSOR ORGANIZATIONS]
In the early years, Women's Christian Associations and YWCAs used the word "Industrial" to refer to any kind of non-professional employment-women earning a living by their own "industry." YWCA Industrial Club members worked in factories, mills, laundries, hotels, department stores, telephone offices, domestic service (known as "household employment" in the YWCA.), etc.
Though the YWCA's original efforts on behalf of employed women did not exclude any type of work, the limited options open to women in the mid-nineteenth century meant that the majority of working women served by the YW were not employed in offices or the professions. This had changed by the end of the century as more and more women found work in offices and retail stores, where the work was clean and "light," the hours were generally shorter, and some opportunities for advancement existed. Many young office workers belonged to the Industrial Club at their Community YWCA, but often felt that issues specific to their work lives were not being addressed there.
Much of the initial "Industrial-Extension" work by the predecessor organizations took place inside factory buildings under the auspices of the employer. The Association was essentially "used by the employer as his agent for welfare work." As they became better acquainted with factory conditions and workers' struggles, YWCA secretaries felt this arrangement compromised their ability to work effectively with and on behalf of the employees. Though the Association needed the financial support provided by employers, it decided it could only accept their money if it was applied to the entire Association and did not specifically finance work with the Industrial women. Clubs that were originally organized "within factory walls" moved off site, but often retained the name of the factory and roster of members drawn from its work rolls. In some cases, Clubs evolved into Industrial Branches affiliated with a central City Association.
When the predecessor organizations merged to form the YWCA of the U.S.A., the National Association augmented the direct work being done under the auspices of Community Associations in what would become its classic fashion: making ongoing studies of the existing conditions to determine workers' needs, and developing methods and techniques to help meet those needs.
Beyond the enrichment and general educational opportunities offered to all YWCA members, the national program for employed women came to include a strong public advocacy component on behalf of workers [see SERIES III. PUBLIC ADVOCACY]; aid in the formation of self-governing Councils of working women; leadership training and administrative support for the Councils; and development of a multitude of ways "interpret" employed women's issues to the general membership.
In 1908 the National Association decided to experiment with serving professional workers, through the establishment of a Cooperating Committee with the Central Club for Nurses in New York City. Nineteenth century advances in the medical profession dramatically altered the nurse's job from that of a domestic helper primarily employed in the home, to professionally trained employees in a rapidly increasing array of new hospitals. In typical YWCA manner, National Staff studied existing conditions, identified needs, and recommended ways the Association might meet those needs. Once the work was established, the Cooperating Committee was absorbed into the YWCA of the City of New York, and the National Association made use of its experience to help formulate program for other professional workers.
In her 1911-12 biennial report to the Method Department, Industrial Secretary Florence Simms noted an overall "change of policy of the Association from the adaptation of the girl to the organization to the adaptation of the organization to the girl.. .," the "natural outgrowth" of which was the "further development of the principle of self-government in the club work." For the program to be truly useful, it had to be initiated and run by the club members and not by YWCA staff.
From 1913 the National Association encouraged "federation" of these small self-governing clubs into larger Councils based in cities or regions. In structure, the Councils mirrored the National Association. Local Clubs banded together into city, state, or regional groups. These self-governing groups gave members a chance to experience democracy, learn leadership and group work techniques, and understand the interdependence of all working women.
Club Councils held at summer camps in 1913 brought representatives from Industrial Clubs to regional conferences at Altamont in New York, Nepawhin in Pennsylvania, and Lake Geneva in Wisconsin. Here, along with the usual YWCA camp activities, delegates discussed ways to widen the influence of Industrial Clubs, suggested plans for further federation of clubs, and made plans for educational work.
In the first few years, Club Councils were primarily concerned with "executive technique," such as how to organize groups and activities and different ways to raise money. By 1917 the Council experience had broadened the industrial member's horizon from "just her own factory" to include the industrial needs of women throughout the country. Attendees were seeing themselves "industrially," making recommendations about how Industrial Clubs might work on behalf of minimum wage laws, advocate for health insurance, and promote efforts aimed at improving working conditions.
The Councils asked the National Association to develop new evening classes "different in many respects from the older type of ukulele and millinery" (The YWCA and Industry, 1928). It included topics such as: furnishing the home and what makes a house a home, as well as economics and labor problems, history, English, and public speaking, legislative questions, and how a city is governed.
Through their Studies and interactions with Club members, Industrial Secretaries on the National staff and in Community Associations had plenty of experience of the struggles of industrial workers, but the YWCA's intense involvement in World War I brought much more direct consciousness of these problems to the Association as a whole. [see SERIES VII. WAR WORK AND DEFENSE SERVICES].
World War I brought a dramatic increase in the number of women "being thrust into business" and prompted the National Association to begin specialized work with business and professional women. Early in 1918 the Association hired its first secretary for work with business and professional women. In May of that year the YWCA sponsored a national conference of business and professional women, who were not necessarily YWCA members, to consult on what kind of work might best serve this constituency. The Business and Professional women responded with appreciation for the work the YW was doing, but had concerns about whether the membership requirement (in order to be a YW member one had to be a member of an Evangelical Protestant church) was appropriate for a national business organization. During the conference, the Business and Professional women established a National Business Women's Committee which had its first meeting immediately following adjournment.
The Committee held its first Convention in St. Louis the following year and decided to form an independent organization, the National Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs. Acknowledging the special needs of younger women, this group encouraged the YWCA to continue its efforts on behalf of their youngest sisters.
In October of 1919 the YWCA called its first National Conference of Industrial Club members "with the hope of phrasing a message" for the first International Congress of Working Women that would "clarify the relationship of Christianity to the present situation of women in industry." At the end of the conference, the delegates submitted a set of resolutions for eventual submission to the YWCA National Convention. The resolutions included a list of standards "which our industrial membership believes might form the basis of favorable working and living conditions for all industrial working women," accompanied by a recommendation that the National Association should promote education on industrial questions among all Association members and that "women should use their newly acquired power of the franchise to secure the writing of these standards into laws."
The resolutions reached the Convention in 1920 in the form of a recommendation that the YWCA adopt as its social program the "Social Ideals of the Churches" which had been articulated by the Federal Council of Churches in 1912. For the first time Industrial Club members took an active part in Convention proceedings, and their speeches from the floor "were quite largely responsible for the passage of that platform."
In "An Historical Outline of the Work of the Industrial Department," Grace Coyle described the import of the moment as the point at which the "social thought of the Association had crystallized sufficiently so that it was ready to take a stand nationally.... [I]t represented the fact that we...as an organization assumed responsibility for changing those [working] conditions until they came nearer to the Christian conception of society as a human brotherhood."
The National Association was so impressed by the activities of Industrial membership during World War I and its Council work after the war, that it voted to authorize formation of a National Industrial Assembly at the 1922 Convention. Assemblies allowed various constituent groups to gather "for acquaintance with one another and for consideration of their part in the life of women through their membership in the YWCA." They functioned like mini-Conventions where the membership debated and approved resolutions and program for Clubs to carry out in the following years. They were autonomous groups authorized to make decisions on behalf of their constituency and subject to the total membership only in matters of consequence to the entire Association. Assemblies selected a National Council (equivalent to the National Board of the YWCA) to draft program and resolutions, plan Assemblies, and oversee progress on projects and program in the interim between Conventions.
The National Association hired its first National Secretary for work with Business and Professional women in 1922 and moved to establish a National Business Assembly at Convention in 1924.
Conferences played a major role in the programs for employed women providing a broadening experience that re-energized members. They were planned by Area Councils and often included National Staff as facilitators. Summer conferences or councils, designed on the model of the traditional student summer conferences, lasted for ten days and were held in inexpensive vacation spots, such as at summer camps or on college campuses. For many they offered "a chance for a real vacation," combined with an opportunity to understand the shared concerns and interdependence of working women. The general educational program included traditional YWCA topics, such as religion, government and citizenship, interracial relations, world fellowship, and Association principles and practices. The "technical hours" were the "setting-up conference" for planning the work for the year. Attendees divided into commissions that worked on subjects such as education; social service; club organization; and issues specific to working women, such as consumer interests, occupational health and safety, trade unions, etc. Personal development activities included writing groups, music, dramatics, and various opportunities for outdoor recreation.
Weekend conferences were an especially strong tradition among Business and Professional Clubs. They were initiated and executed by Business and Professional staff and club members of several Community Associations in geographic proximity. They provided opportunities for conference chairs to gather the "thinking and concerns" of the members and convey that to Area Councils and summer conferences. National staff attended whenever possible.
Both Councils also sponsored yearly events to celebrate their unity and common concerns with a banquet and program held on the same night. For Business and Professional Clubs the event was known as the Nation-wide Observance (later, World-wide Observance). The Industrial Club version was known as National Industrial Progress Day.
To bring working women's concerns to the full Association and the general public, Eleanor Coit, National Industrial Secretary, encouraged Industrial Secretaries in Community Associations to use their regular contact with industrial members to gather "a fund of human experience that needs to get into the consciousness of the public." Feeling acutely the inadequacy of the national research staff, Coit encouraged local secretaries to use the "story method" to collect information. The main emphases of the program for 1926-27 were married women in industry and the racial factor in industry.
National staff spent considerable time on labor education in the 1930s, whether participating in YWCA conferences or in the Bryn Mawr and Wisconsin Summer Schools for women in industry.
"More and more thinking men and women are realizing how largely shortages in people's lives are due to shortages in their education. A large percentage of the membership of the YWCA consists of women whose education has been cut short at an early age, and who are for this reason seriously handicapped not only in the business of earning a living, but also in the business of living. To enable these women to bridge over the gaps in their education is, therefore, becoming an increasingly important concern of this organization, especially now that women are assuming heavier responsibilities as citizens than they have ever shouldered before" (When Labor Goes to School, 1920).
By the end of World War I, the National Association had developed relatively elaborate programs for Industrial, Business and Professional, and eventually Agricultural workers with associated specialist staff. The YWCA was always somewhat ambivalent about whether the various groups of employed women were different enough to warrant separate groups. While some issues were unique to a particular category of job, many issues were shared and much of the general YWCA program was essentially identical for all groups of working women. With the loss of wartime and continuation funding and the onset of the Great Depression, it became difficult for the National Association to continue to support the programs and for the Club members to afford conferences and travel to council meetings.
During the Depression, the two Councils were both heavily involved in work on the problems related to the widespread unemployment. A 1928 Convention Action called for Community Associations to devise methods for aiding the unemployed in their area, and charged the National Association to cooperate with other organizations to "promote adequate protection and remedial measures in the stabilization of employment." Results of local studies and articles by outside experts and YWCA staff were collected together in a "Symposium" for use at the 1930 Convention. Supplementary budget appropriations in 1931 supported research and development of a group of publications on how to deal with the challenges, including such topics as making constructive use of enforced leisure time, the social consequences of widespread unemployment, and services for transient and homeless women.
The National Association's mid-1930s plan to concentrate on the Association "as a whole" rather than its constituent parts meant that the Councils got less support and participation from National staff. Strong interest, particularly in the Industrial Council, kept employed women's Councils going through World War II despite dwindling membership.
By the late 1940s the Councils began to look for ways to revitalize the programs for working women. They asked for increased national support, particularly in the form of studies. The Business, Professional, and Industrial Experimentation Committee carried out experimental studies in eleven selected communities to find new ways of strengthening program with young employed women.
The National Board appointed an Ad Hoc Committee to Study the Future of Business, Professional and Industrial Assembly and Council Structure and its related conferences and program in 1948. Given the National Association's general movement away from programs aimed at constituent groups, part of the Committee's charge was to determine whether the National Association should continue to support the Councils at all. Its January 1949 report proposed combining the two Councils into a single National Employed Women's Council with equal numbers of members drawn from the Industrial and Business and Professional constituency. While B and P accepted the idea, the Industrial Council was less enthusiastic. In the end, they devised a compromise plan in which the two Assemblies would meet together as the National Employed Women's Coordinating Assembly which would have complete responsibility for matters of mutual concern, such as dues, program, trends, and cooperation, and each would continue to meet separately on matters specific to the different types of work.
As of 1950 National oversight of the work with employed women became the responsibility of the Young Adult Committee/Council which had general responsibility for all members not in high school or college, whether in the workforce or not. [See Subseries E. Young Adults.]
Some study and experimentation continued until 1952, but the self-governing groups for employed women did not ultimately survive. Efforts on behalf of working women on the national level continued primarily as part of the Public Advocacy program. The National Association also sponsored or co-sponsored periodic conferences or consultations on women and work.
As a result of the Economic Opportunity Act of 1964, the National Association got involved in two new projects for employed women in the late 1960s: the Business Office Culture Project, and the Job-Corps YWCA Extension Residence Program. Both of these projects were funded by the U.S. Department of Labor, administered by the National Association, and carried out in selected Community Associations. The Business Office Culture Project (circa 1968-69) provided technical training and an introduction to the "culture" of the business world. The National Association's involvement with Job-Corps (1967-75) was to run small (15-30 person) residences for young women who had completed the Job-Corps vocational training program. Here the trainees could gain experience living and working independently with support and supervision from YWCA counselors and program specialists. The Government did not renew the national contract as of the spring of 1975, but it encouraged Job Corps Regional Offices to enter into contracts with local YWCAs.
HOUSEHOLD EMPLOYMENT
As the National Association grew, it noted an increasing number of Industrial Club members in domestic service, or "Household Employment," particularly in its "Colored" Branches. The National Association made regular studies and surveys of conditions beginning in 1915 with the appointment of the Commission on Household Employment. In 1928 it participated in the formation of the National Committee on Employer-Employee Relationships in the Home, which later evolved into the National Council on Household Employment. The YWCA was one of the Council's cooperating agencies with a member on its Board. The National Association also advocated for a voluntary employer-employee agreement covering issues such as maximum hours, minimum wage, living arrangements, regular payment of wages, etc.
The Industrial Assembly took up the subject at its 1925 Conferences and adopted it as one of its Projects in 1931. The National Association and the Industrial Assembly collected data on working conditions and training programs. With the staff reductions and reorganization of the early 1930s, the work, which had been associated with the Industrial Department, became "loosely" attached to Public Affairs through its Subcommittee on Household Employment. This Subcommittee gathered data from the various groups studying the "household employment problem" in the YWCA. Because YWCA constituency included both employers and employees, the Subcommittee felt the YWCA constituted "the best working laboratory in the world" for studying the situation. Their recommended program for improving employer-employee relations included study and discussion groups, promotion of a voluntary agreement on employment terms, legislation, and cooperative relationships with organized groups of employers and employees.
By the late 1930s this Subcommittee was mainly advocating for legislation, such as the inclusion of domestic employees in the Social Security program. Beginning in the mid-1940s discussions about the general decline in participation of working women in the YWCA and ever decreasing numbers of domestic workers included the decision that the Association could not continue to devote part of its limited resources to household employment issues.
Administrative History
1907-08 Industrial Secretary, Association Extension Committee in the Home Department and regional Field Secretaries in Field Dept
1909-18 Home Department name changed to Department of Method
1918-22 large staff expansion associated with World War I, some staff part of War Work Council
1919-23 Department of Method name changed to Research and Method
1923-32 Industrial Department and Department of Work with Business and Professional Women under Field Division (first staff for B and P)
1932 National Services Division
1933-39 Membership Program under Leadership Division
1940-45 Group Interests under Community Division